（英格兰北部 约克郡 庞蒂弗拉克特城堡）
国王即将驾到
The King approaches!
圣驾将至
His Majesty's coming!
预备
Ready!
立正
Attention!
向右转
Right turn!
就绪
Ready!
拉尔夫爵士 各位大人以及先生们
Sir Ralph, my lords and gentlemen,
感谢上帝 我终于能来到北部
I thank God at last, I have been able to come among.
来到约克郡 来到我忠实的仆人中间
my faithful servants in Yorkshire and the North.
请允许我介绍我的妻子
Allow me to introduce my wife,
- 凯瑟琳王后 - 王后陛下
- Queen Katherine. - Your Majesty.
你们已见过我的长女 玛丽女士
And you know my eldest daughter, the Lady Mary.
您好 女士
My Lady.
欢迎陛下以及各位大人
Your Majesties, and all those with you.
光临庞蒂弗拉克特城堡
are welcome to Pontefract Castle.
我相信此行将使你们
I trust your stay here will bring you.
愉悦欢喜 获利良多
both pleasure and profit.
- 拉尔夫爵士 - 陛下
- Sir Ralph. - Your Majesty.
卡尔佩珀
Culpepper!
今晚我要与王后共寝
I will sleep with the Queen tonight.
- 带她来见我 - 遵旨
- Bring her to me. - Majesty.
公爵大人 国王看起来精神抖擞
The King seems in good spirits, your Grace.
拉尔夫爵士 陛下圣体十分安康
His Majesty is very well, Sir Ralph.
王后新娶 壮志又起
He has both a new Queen and it seems a new lease on life.
此处诸事进展顺利
His progress here has been joyful.
四方之民蜂拥俱至竭诚恭迎圣驾
Crowds have come out to cheer him.
显赫之士发表演说极尽赞美之辞
and eminent men have made speeches to praise him.
不久还会有人前来恭迎圣驾
There will be men come here too, now and in a while…
是那些曾揭竿造反的叛逆之徒
men who once wore the emblem of…
现到此以示悔恨羞愧之意
rebellion came now to express their shame for it.
向右转 撤退
Right men, pull out!
大人 欢迎回到庞蒂弗拉克特城堡
Welcome back to Pontefract Castle, your Grace.
恕我冒昧
Forgive me.
故地重游 此情此景一定使大人忆起往昔
These walls must remind your Grace of other times.
的确如此
They do.
拉尔夫爵士 我不得不说
I must confess to you, Sir Ralph,
幽灵鬼魅回荡于此
that this hall is filled with ghostly presences.
故人旧事实难忘怀
that I should rather forget.
对我来说也是如此
For me, too.
我知道他卑颜屈膝投靠叛贼
I know he was an arch traitor,
但达西大人 老汤
but my Lord Darcy-Old Tom.
似乎仍在城垛间盘桓
he still seems to haunt these battlements.
我内心矛盾 仍希望在就寝之时见到他
I half expect to see him on my way to bed.
请你以诚相告
Tell me, truly:
没有圣人 没有信仰 没有修道院
How do the people cope here without their saints,
此处民众何以为生
their superstitions, their monasteries?
壁龛空无一物
There are some a few.
教堂烛台不再 亦无对逝者的祷告之音
who still grumble at the empty niches in the churches,
仍有少数人对此心存怨言
the absence of candles and prayers for the dead.
但自秘书大臣克伦威尔被斩
But it seems with the death of Secretary Cromwell.
复辟的热情似乎也逐渐消退
that the reforming zeal has slackened.
您…
You there…
或又是如何 公爵大人
Or has it? No one knows, your Grace,
国王陛下是要继续弃圣坛于不顾
whether the King means to continue stripping the altars,
还是回归旧道 这无人知晓
or return to the old ways.
民众常惧于开口
They are often afraid to open their mouths,
生怕祸从口出
in case they should say the wrong thing.
君心难测 拉尔夫爵士
It is not always easy to read the King's mind, Sir Ralph.
陛下
Majesty.
My Lady.
- 罗彻福德夫人 - 卡尔佩珀大人
- Lady Rochford. - Master Culpepper.
陛下准备好接见你了
His Majesty is ready to receive you.
等会见吗
Later?
陛下 王后驾到
Your Majesty, the Queen is here.
陛下
Your Majesty.
我刚听闻罗马皇帝
I have just heard that the Emperor.
和法兰西国王关系紧张 一触即发
and the King of France are on the brink of war.
陛下一定觉得
Surely your Majesty does not want to see me…
此时见我不合时宜
at… such a time?
为何
Why?
因为
Because…
您还有要事在身
you have more important matters.
会比你还重要吗
More important than you?
是的
Yes.
让他们开战去吧
Let them have their war.
你可知何人曾命丧于这座城堡
Do you know who died here, in this castle?
不 我是指重要人物
No. Important men.
不知道
No.
理查二世被废黜后 就死于这里
Richard the Second died here, after he was deposed.
他当时年仅33岁
He was 33 years of age.
他们将他囚禁于此 活活饿死了他
They kept him here as a prisoner. They starved him to death.
可怜的亡魂
Poor ghost.
他错就错在亲近少数派
He made the mistake of favouring.
疏远了多数派
lesser men over greater ones.
因此大家才决定
For such mean creatures are determined.
不仅要篡夺王权
not just to usurp the nobility,
还要将我们贵族一同毁灭
but to destroy us altogether.
大人 也许有时候的确如此
Sometimes, my Lord, it may be so.
但陛下所赐官职和地位
But surely the King is right where he gives offices.
都是给了受之无愧之人
and dignities to those with the right qualities?
不 陛下提拔的那帮贱民
No. Those men that are made by the King of vile birth.
玷污了我们贵族的高贵血统
have been the distraction of all the nobility of this realm!
只要陛下魂归天命
And if God calls away the King,
- 他们便会为此付出代价 - 大人
- They will suffer for it! - My Lord,
当心 别诅咒陛下的性命
be careful not to wish the King's life away.
这是叛国之罪
That is treason!
托马斯大人
Sir Thomas,
我想你朋友萨里大人正咒骂你呢
I think your friend Surrey is snarling at you.
国王驾到
His Majesty, the King!
陛下 这位是西维尔先生
Mr. Sidwell, your Majesty.
陛下 作为您卑微的仆人
Your Majesty, we your humble servants confess.
我等贱民承认 我们的叛乱
that we wretches have most grievously, wantonly,
实属不忠 不孝 不义之举
and heinously offended your Majesty.
并且无理 无序 无情地
in the most unnatural, odious, and distasteful acts.
冒犯了陛下的盛威
of outrageous disobedience and traitorous rebellion.
若陛下仍余怒未消
We beg your Majesty to rid your mind of any relics of indignation.
我等谨请陛下息怒
you might still harbour against us,
日后定当每日为陛下祈福
and we pray henceforward to pray ceaselessly for your preservation,
为您的王后 您的子嗣 爱德华王子祈福
and for that of your queen and of your son, the Prince Edward,
愿万能的上帝保佑我们
so God Almighty help us!
我对汝等并无怒意
I harbour no relics of indignation against you.
并且 鉴于你们现在的忠心表现
And for these shows of loyalty.
我原谅你们的一切罪过
I forgive you all your trespasses against us.
国王万岁
Long live the King!
玛丽·都铎女士驾到
The Lady Mary Tudor.
她来了
There she is.
玛丽女士 上帝保佑你
Lady Mary, God bless you!
上帝保佑陛下
God bless your Majesty!
夫人 醒醒
My Lady! My Lady! Wake up!
琼
Joan?
几时了
What time?
看
Look.
上帝保佑玛丽女士
God bless Lady Mary!
我愿汝等为陛下祷告
I want you to say a prayer for his Grace, the King's Majesty.
愿陛下的统治绵延万世
We pray for his Majesty's long and blessed reign.
愿陛下万寿无疆
and for his good health.
以圣母玛丽亚之名
In the name of the Blessed Virgin.
她唯一的儿子为了我们的罪过而殉难
whose only Son died in agony for our sins.
以圣父圣子和圣灵之名
In the name of the Father, Son,
我保佑你们所有人
and Holy Ghost, I bless all of you.
一切都会好转
All shall be well.
一切终会重回正轨
All manner of things shall be well.
赞美上帝
Benedictus Deus.
上帝保佑陛下
God bless his Majesty!
都铎王朝 亘古长存
Long live the house of Tudor!
我要做…
I would be…
一只山鹬
a woodcock.
选得好
Good choice.
因为它是只雄鸟（亦指男性生殖器）
Because it's a cock.
怎么了
What is it?
是他
It's him!
是他吧
It is him, isn't it?
弗兰西斯·迪尔罕先生 陛下
Mr. Francis Dereham, your Majesty.
陛下
Your Majesty.
迪尔罕先生
Mr. Dereham.
陛下 请叫我弗兰西斯
Francis, please… your Majesty.
你为何来此
Why have you come here?
我来呈交此物予陛下
I came to give you this.
何物
What is it?
公爵夫人的引荐信
A letter of recommendation from the Dowager Duchess.
您还记得公爵夫人吧 陛下
You remember the Duchess, don't you, your Majesty?
你要这信有何用
Why do you need such a letter?
若我有心仕途
I believe such a thing.
你理应举荐我
is obligatory if one is seeking employment.
你看过信就知道
When you read it, you will see that since.
和你一别之后 我在公爵夫人家
we last met I have held a number of responsible positions.
担任过不少要职
in the Duchess's household,
她对我赞不绝口
for which she freely commends me.
弗朗西斯 让我举荐你
It is not possible for me to offer you employment…
这不大可能
Francis.
为什么呢
But why not?
服侍你的人一定不能少
You must keep a large establishment.
你需要文书吗
But do you have a secretary?
我会做得很出色
I would make an excellent secretary.
我为何不能任用你 你心里清楚
Surely you can understand why I cannot offer you anything?
但你任用了琼·布尔默吧
But you employed Joan Bulmer, didn't you?
她知道得不比我少
And she knows what I know.
你何必厚此薄彼
So what is the difference?
我看是你的侍女宣我觐见
I was bound to notice that one of your ladies announced me.
你难道没有侍从吗
Does that mean you have no usher for your chamber?
以您的身份
I am very sure you ought to,
理应需要侍从
considering who you are.
我不能这么做
I can't…
您当然可以 陛下
But you can, your Majesty.
您毕竟是英格兰的王后
You are, after all, the Queen of England.
您可以为所欲为
You can do as you will.
好吧
All right.
你要谨言慎行
Just take care what words you speak!
遵命
Your Majesty.
陛下 法国大使到
Your Majesty, the French Ambassador.
- 大使先生 - 陛下
- Excellency! - Your Majesty.
相信阁下定会向贵国王上
I trust you will not forget to convey to your master.
转达今日所见之事
what you have seen here today:
之前那上千名暴民
Thousands of former rebels come to offer.
向他们认定的国王忏悔
their supplication to their anointed King!
此等大事
I will, of course,
我定当禀报吾王
convey these tremendous events to his Majesty.
不 今日之事足以让他明白
No. You will tell him, based on what you have seen,
企图以宗教分歧
that it would be foolish.
煽动无知民众闹事
to contemplate an invasion of this island.
趁机攻打我国
in the mistaken belief that it is riven.
实属不智之举
with religious discord and full of discontented men.
陛下 我担保
Majesty, I am very sure.
吾王绝无此意
that my master has no such plans.
恰恰相反 吾王将英格兰视为
On the contrary, he regards England as his natural ally.
对抗罗马帝国的天生盟友
against the Emperor.
愿如阁下所言
Good. Excellency.
公爵大人 约克一行准备如何
Your Grace, what preparations are made for our visit to York?
回陛下 议院已在圣玛丽旧教堂为您打点妥当
Majesty, chambers are being made ready for your Majesty.
并将陛下所用挂毯和餐具
in the former abbey of St. Mary, and furnished.
由伦敦运至此处
with your Majesty's tapestries and plate brought from London.
随侍之人会在教堂内驻扎
Tents are also being erected in the Abbey grounds.
以护您周全
to accommodate your court.
詹姆士国王驾临后也是如此
and that of King James's court when he arrives.
很好
Good.
宝贝儿 你还好吗
Sweetheart, how are you?
我很好 多谢陛下关怀
I am well, thank you… your Majesty.
我要禀告陛下 我今日在自己宫中
I must tell your Majesty that today I appointed.
新任命了一位文书兼侍从
a new Private Secretary and Usher to my Chambers.
那么 你想现在颁布诏命吗
What will you write letters now?
您允许吗
You don't mind?
当然 我对你说过 尽可随心所欲
Of course not. I've told you: you must do what you will.
谢谢
Thank you.
是叔叔
Uncle.
叔叔
王后 恭祝您身体健康
Madam, your good health!
多谢 公爵大人
Thank you, your Grace.
琼 你好啊
Hello, Joan.
仿佛回到从前吧
Just like old times?
不
No.
今非昔比 弗朗西斯 你很清楚
These times is different, Francis. You know that very well.
想想看啊 琼 我们的小凯特
Just imagine, Joanie! Our Kate,
如今竟成了英格兰的王后
our little Katie is Queen of England.
她不再是我们的小凯特了
She's not our Kate anymore.
她已嫁做人妇
She belongs to him.
她是国王的女人 你最好记住这点
She belongs to the King, and don't you forget it.
你别打什么主意
Don't you ever get any ideas into that mind of yours.
你说什么
What kind of ideas?
我说什么你很清楚
You know very well what I'm talking about.
弗朗西斯 往事不再
Those days are over, Francis.
不会重来
They're dead!
如今过得很好
This is a good living.
这曾是你我梦寐以求的生活
This is the highest living you or I could ever dream of!
看在上帝份儿上 别毁了这份幸福
For God's sake, don't spoil it.
为我们俩 也为了她
Not for us and not for her!
我睡哪里
So… where am I to sleep?
不睡这里 不和我们一起
Not here. Not with us!
老天
For heaven's sake…
你要和国王的侍从住在一起
you must ask the King's chamberlain for a place.
明白吗
Do you understand?
明白
I suppose so.
你什么意思
What's that?
不过是个吻
Just a kiss.
为老朋友的情谊
For old times' sake!
谁在那儿
Who's there?
达西大人
My Lord Darcy.
公爵大人
Your Grace.
你已经死了
You're dead.
是的 但却未得安息
Yes… but not yet at rest.
活着的人未能觉察
The living don't know that the recent dead.
近来总有亡魂萦绕
are always around them.
他们到处忏悔
We go here and there, to do penance,
以佑周围亲人平安
to make sure our relatives are well,
之后我们才能安心上路
while we await our second death.
为何来找我说这些
Why do you appear to me?
我是已死之人
I am among the Dead.
终日与那些曾遭你弑戮
I have joined the ghosts.
或曾蒙你恩泽的亡灵为伴
of all your victims, your Grace.
但不必太过悲伤
But do not grieve too much,
其境遇 亦非凄苦
for they are not bitter.
尽管孩子们曾整日无虑
Even the children think of nothing.
但欢快忘忧的童年终会止步
but stopping this endless motion,
嬉闹玩耍的岁月也终会落幕
this rushing here and there,
一如曾经葱嵘尘世间的你我
like doubles of our earthly selves.
当年华老去 恩仇泯逝之后
And when we have settled all our accounts,
天使终会带着我们埋骨天国
the angels will come to take us to the place of rest.
我希望你不要再缠着我
I wish you had not bothered me.
但此刻 我不愿让你离去
But now I would not have you go.
我并非真的在你面前
I am not really here.
但我能看到你
But I can see you.
能听见你
and hear you.
你是达西
You are Darcy.
我不是达西 我是虚无的魂魄
I am not Darcy! I am nothing!
如果你伸出手来摸我
If you reached out your hand.
摸到的 就只有空气
to touch me, it would find only air.
我很抱歉 我背叛了你
I'm sorry that I betrayed you.
请原谅我
Forgive me.
老汤
Old Tom.
我做不到
I can't do that.
生者是如此自私
The living are so selfish.
只顾及自己的得失
They can think of nothing but themselves.
（温莎城堡）
[拉丁语]如我
Qui mihi.
少壮不努力
discipulus puer es…
如我少壮…
Qui mihi… dis…
爱德华
Edward,
现在凑近些听
now listen closely.
你有一位家庭教师
When you have a tutor,
一定要跟她学习这些知识
you have to learn these things, Edward.
拉丁语
Cupis atque…
doceri… Cupis…
拉丁语
atque doc…
你想出去玩吗
You want to go and play?
是的 如果你允许的话 姐姐
Yes, if it please you, sister.
爱德华 他日你定能成为伟大的国君
One day you will be a great King, Edward.
我知道你能做到
I know you will be.
刚毅果敢
And very strong.
且公正仁慈
But also fair and merciful.
我望你首先成为一名正直的君王
I want you to be a just ruler,
那将是你成就一代明君的必经之路
and then indeed you shall be a great King.
现在 出去玩吧
Now go along and play.
谢谢 伊丽莎白
Thank you, Elizabeth.
上帝保佑你
And God bless you!
托马斯·卡尔佩珀先生求见
Mr. Thomas Culpepper.
- 陛下 - 遵命 陛下
- My Lady. Yes Majesty. - Your Majesty.
那是谁
Who is that?
他是弗朗西斯·迪尔罕
His name is Francis Dereham.
他从何而来
But where did he come from?
我很久以前就认识他了
I knew him a long time ago.
我们都曾和公爵遗孀一起生活过
We both lived with the Dowager Duchess.
是她写信举荐他过来
She wrote to me recommending his services.
你了解他多少
How well did you know him?
你到底想说些什么
What are you trying to say?
你对他 了解多少
How well did you know him?
我们当时还小
We were children!
你早就不是孩子了
You were never a child. Ever!
这你最清楚
You should know!
别碰我
Don't touch me!
别再用你的脏手碰我
Don't ever touch me like that!
你不知道我的身份吗
Don't you know who I am?
还是不清楚我的权力
Or what I could do to you?
你不会认为自己是我的唯一吧
You don't think you're the only one, do you?
如你这般的男宠 又何止十数
I have a store of other lovers beside you!
现在 给我滚出去 滚出去
Now get out! Get out!
遵命 陛下
Your Majesty.
（约克大教堂）
主教大人
Your Grace!
国王陛下
Your Majesty.
大英帝国教会虔诚的神职人员
The devoted clergy of your Majesty's Church of England,
以及约克郡各界名流贵绅
and the nobility and loyal gentlemen of York,
恭迎陛下驾到
welcome you most heartily.
陛下对吾等过去所犯的恶劣罪行
In gratitude for your Majesty's gracious pardon.
宽仁慈厚 既往不咎
of our previous, and grievous, sins,
吾等诚心请陛下收下这些金子
We hope your Majesty will accept these purses of gold.
陛下
Majesty.
感谢我主的恩典
We thank your Grace.
感谢约克郡人民
We thank York!
为苏格兰国王的来访都安排妥当了吗
Is everything prepared for the King of Scotland's visit?
是的 陛下
Yes, your Majesty.
詹姆斯国王正在等待过境
King James is waiting across the border.
我已经派出信使 告知其境内保证一路安全
I have sent post horses and messages of reassurance to him.
何必如此 他害怕什么
Why? What is he afraid of?
他怕我们会杀了他吗
Does he think we're going to kill him?
是同一个人吗
And it's the same one?
那个曾在夜里来和她会面 她还曾对其许诺
The one who visited her at night? To whom she was promised?
是的 就是同一个人
Yes, my Lady. It's the same gentleman.
我能用这个博您芳心吗
Can I interest you in this?
他变化不大
He has not changed much.
他一贯那么放肆吗
Was he always so familiar?
他就是那种人
That is his way.
上帝保佑
Lord help us.
再添些酒吗 陛下
More wine, my Lady?
- 不必 谢谢 - 来吧
- No. Thank you. - Oh, come on.
就一点 再来点
Just a little? One more.
我说不必 迪尔罕先生
I said no, Mr. Dereham.
谢谢您
Thank you.
我主耶稣
Christ!
我要就寝了
I'm going to bed.
- 陛下 - 女士们
- Your Majesty. - Ladies?
- 陛下 - 来吧 女士们
- Your Majesty. - Come, ladies.
女士们
Ladies.
迪尔罕先生 我不知道您是谁
Mr. Dereham…I don't know who you are,
但您无权对英国王后
but you have no right to be so familiar.
如此放肆
with the Queen of England!
也不可在她面前出言亵渎
Or blaspheme in her presence.
菲尔先生
Mr. Fell,
我对英国王后的了解 远远超过您
I know the Queen of England a great deal better than you do.
我看未必
I don't think so.
什么叫 我看未必
What do you mean: "I don't think so"?
她叫凯瑟琳·霍华德
Her name is Katherine Howard,
我认识她已经很久了
and I've known her a long time.
我们曾经过从甚密
We used to be very close.
甚密到你无法想象
Very close.
晚安 可爱的爱德华
Good night, sweet Edward.
布莱恩夫人
Lady Bryan!
布莱恩夫人 快来
Lady Bryan! Come quickly!
他发烧了 摸摸他的头
He has a fever. Feel his head.
- 快召医师 跑着去 - 是 夫人
- Go fetch a physician. Run! - Yes Madam.
- 给赫福德大人捎个信 - 是 夫人
- Send a message to my Lord Hertford. - Yes my Lady.
可怜的孩子
Poor lamb!
您的行为是十足的侮辱王威
Your behaviour is a complete outrage.
我要您发誓 迪尔罕先生
I want you to promise, Mr. Dereham,
发誓从现在起 您将不再口出任何
that from now on you will not speak of the Queen.
有辱王后陛下威仪的言语
in ways which offend her proper dignity.
何来威仪可言
Her dignity!
我想怎么说就怎么说她
I shall speak of her how I like.
但您绝不可如此放肆
But you must not be so familiar.
放肆
So familiar?
相信我 我跟她可熟了
Believe me, I am very familiar with her.
看在上帝的份上 先生
For God sake's, man!
您满口胡言乱语只会害了您自己
Your bragging and your lies only harm yourself.
我胡说
My lies?
你说我胡说 好吧 菲尔先生
You think that I am lying? Let me tell you something, Mr. Fell.
我对凯瑟琳·霍华德非常了解
I know Katherine Howard well enough,
我可把玩过她的私处
for I have had her by the cunt.
上帝啊 先生
My God, man!
而这只是我所熟知她的一小部分
and I would know it among a hundred others.
我要你替我给他捎个口信
I want you to give him a message.
给谁 陛下
Who, your Majesty?
你知道是谁
You know who!
卡尔佩珀
Culpepper!
- 告诉他 我一定要见他 - 夫人
- Tell him… I must see him. - My Lady…
告诉他有个通道可通我的房间
Tell him there is a way into my chamber.
让他明天来 等国王睡了
Tell him to come tomorrow, when the King is asleep.
怎么回事
What is it?
类似第三级高烧 赫福德大人
Some kind of tertiary fever, my Lord Hertford.
有危险吗
Is he in danger?
他的性命是否堪忧 回答我
Is his life in danger? Answer me!
如果高烧不退 恐有危险
If the fever persists, then perhaps.
我们还是有办法的 大人
We do have some remedies, my Lord.
要不要通知国王
Shall we tell the King?
不
No.
倘若他决议缩短行程 尽快赶回
If he felt obliged to curtail his progress and hurry back,
结果王子却生命垂危 这可如何是好
only to find the Prince quite recovered…
给我治好他 看在上帝的份上
Apply your remedies. For God's sake.
也为了国家的安宁
and for the sake of peace in this realm.
别让他撒手人寰
don't let him die.
这很有意思
It's very interesting.
那他是他的表亲吧 对吗
It's his cousin, is it not?
凯特
Kate.
- 陛下 - 陛下
- Your Majesty. - Your Majesty.
下午好 女士们
Good afternoon, ladies.
陛下
Your Majesty.
抱歉丢下您一人如此之久
I am sorry I have left you so much alone.
我跟议会有诸多国事要议
I have had much to do with Council and other matters.
现在 你知道 我的侄子 苏格兰国王詹姆斯
Now, as you know, my nephew, James, King of Scots,
不久将莅临到访
is due to visit here presently.
我们将签署一项和平条款
We are to sign a peace treaty.
然后我们就直接回伦敦 我保证
And then we shall straight back to London. I promise.
一切谨遵陛下所愿
I am at your Majesty's command.
一如既往
Always.
跟我说说 有没有怀上孩子的迹象
Now tell me, is there any sign that you may be with child?
先生们
Gentlemen.
听说苏格兰国王要来了
I hear the King of Scotland is coming!
约克这下可得挤满
York will be full of drunken Scots.
身强力壮的苏格兰醉汉
with their brawny arms and togas.
女士们你们可有福啦
What a boon for you ladies!
坐下 迪尔罕先生
Sit down, Mr. Dereham.
- 信儿给我送到了吗 - 送了
- Did you send the message? - Yes.
他来吗
Will he come?
我们认识一个苏格兰人吧
We knew a Scot, didn't we?
他叫什么来着
What was his name?
你记得吗 叫什么来着
Do you remember? What was it?
曼内克斯
Manox.
你记得曼内克斯吧
You remember Manox?
先生
Sir?
迪尔罕先生
Mr. Dereham!
琼 你一定记得曼内克斯吧
Joan, you must remember Manox?
我知道你和他
I think you and he…
够了 迪尔罕先生
That's quite enough, Mr. Dereham.
女士们
Ladies.
陛下
Your Majesty.
先生们
Gentlemen.
你怎敢如此无礼
How dare you!
我要报告国王陛下
I shall tell the King.
他该知道 他的妻子被她的仆从如此恶劣对待
He ought to know how beggardly his wife's servants treat her.
去你的 菲尔
Damn you, Fell!
- 你去死 - 迪尔罕先生 住手
- Damn you. - Mr. Dereham! Stop it!
快住手
Stop it now!
您在忙什么 大人
What's that, my Lord?
没什么 无聊之作
Oh, nothing. A trifle.
我敢说萨里伯爵的「无聊之作」
I daresay the Earl of Surrey's "Trifles" will.
有朝一日会成为不朽篇章
someday be regarded as some of our greatest poesy.
那我斗胆请大人过目
Then I daresay your Grace can read it.
我以十四行诗的格式
It's a translation, in sonnet form,
翻译马提雅尔的铭词集
of one of Martial's epigrams.
这当然是罗马诗歌 但无关紧要
That is, of course, the Roman poet-but that doesn't matter.
描写的是和谐生活
It's about the happy life.
中庸之道
The Golden Mean.
「乐活何处有 我自寻踪去
"The happy life be these, I find.
千金身外物 何须费心机
"The riches left, not got with pain.
春华待秋实 心静如止水
"The fruitful ground; the quiet mind.
君子坦荡荡 小人长戚戚
"The equal friend; no grudge nor strife.
无法令之责 无铁腕之治
"No charge of rule nor governance.
无疾病之忧 惟康健之体
"Without disease, the healthful life.
大智从率直
"Wisdom joined with simplicity.
长夜无愁绪「
"The night discharged of all care."
心静如止水
The quiet mind.
长夜无愁绪
The night discharged of all care.
大智从率直
Wisdom joined with simplicity.
真令人无限向往
My God, how I wish these things were true.
大人 诗中所言 您得享几样
Which of these, your Grace, do you not have?
样样皆无
All of them.
如此 大人与我相同
Then you are like me.
更有一切罗马公民
And like all the Romans.
一切山野村夫
And all the Barbarians.
前之古人 后之来者
And all the generations before us…
莫不与你我相同
and all those yet to come.
心静如止水 此种境界
For who does not wish, or rest, with all their heart.
谁不渴望
for the quiet mind?
试问这世上谁曾做到
Tell me a single soul who has ever found it?
托马斯
Thomas.
这么说 你改变心意了
You've changed your mind, then?
不
No, no.
我说过 我爱你
I love you. I told you.
除了见你 我别无所求
I long for nothing so much as to see you.
见不到你 我心若死灰
It makes my heart die when I can't see you.
我也爱你
I love you, too.
至于那个迪尔罕
But this Dereham…
你得让他消失
you have to get rid of him.
是的 我知道 我会的
Yes, I know. And I will.
我保证 回到伦敦就处理这事
I promise. When we get back to London.
你没生气吧
You're not still angry with me?
别生我的气
Please don't be angry with me.
我愿唯你是从
I want to be at your commandment.
你知道我要什么
You know what I want.
来吧
Do it!
很好
Yes.
这就对了
That's it.
好极了 宝贝儿
Ah, yes. That's it, my sweet.
我的小傻瓜
My own sweet little fool.
这是陛下送给苏格兰国王的礼物
Your Majesty's gift to the King of Scotland.
何事 速速报来
Well! What do you have to say? Speak!
陛下
Majesty,
苏格兰国王并未践约
the King of Scotland is not coming.
他已返回爱丁堡
He has gone back to Edinburgh.
更糟的是 愿神宽恕他们
But worse! O that God could forgive them!
一支苏格兰军队悍然越境
A Scottish army has ridden over the border and is harrying.
大肆侵扰我国人民 烧抢掳掠
our people, spoiling fields, burning barns,
若有反抗 便大开杀戒
and killing all those who oppose them.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas!
陛下有何吩咐
Majesty.
你指挥我国边境驻军发动反击
You will order our troops on the border to retaliate,
以彼之道 还施彼身
with spoils, burnings and killings.
此仇当以三倍偿之
Three hurts to every one of ours.
明白吗
Do you understand?
遵命 陛下 臣即刻去办
Yes, your Majesty. I am straight away to that business.
陛下
Majesty.
有事快报 否则斩下你的舌头
What do you want? Speak or I will cut out your tongue!
启禀陛下 您的儿子
I am to tell you that your son,
身在温莎的爱德华王子现已病危
Prince Edward, is dangerously ill at Windsor.
陛下
Your Majesty.
圣父 请保佑我弟弟爱德华
Blessed Father, have mercy on my brother Edward.
他系国家之希望
Qui sedes ad dexteram Patris Filim.
父亲
Father.
大人 通知伦敦主教
My Lord, send for the Bishop of London.
让他在王家教堂准备一场特别的弥撒
Tell him to prepare a special Mass in the Chapel Royal,
感谢神佑朕的妻儿
to give thanks to God for my son and for my wife.
遵命 陛下
Yes, your Majesty.
上帝与你同在
Dominus vobiscum.
神之精神永存
Et cum spiritu tuo.
以圣父 圣子
In the name of the Father, Son,
和圣灵的名义
and Holy Ghost.
今天 在所有圣徒面前
On this Day of All Saints,
国王陛下衷心感谢神赐佳偶
his Majesty wishes to thank God for blessing him.
完璧无瑕的凯瑟琳王后
with so perfect a companion as Queen Katherine.
诚如陛下所言
In his Majesty's own words:
「主啊 我当感谢你
"I render thanks to Thee, O Lord,
历尽千般磨难
that after so many strange accidents.
终有完美婚姻
that have befallen my marriages,
你欣然赐我娇妻
Thou hast been pleased to give me a wife.
佳人此刻在旁 全然合我心意「
so entirely conformed to my inclinations as her I now have."
在此光荣圣所
Gaudeamus omnes in Domono,
普天同祝
diem festum celebrantes.
共庆佳节
sub honore sanctorum omnium…